So little Billy goes to school,
إذاً، يذهب بيلي الصغير الى المدرسة،
and he sits down and the teacher says,
ويجلس ثم يقول المعلم،
"What does your father do?"
" ماذا يعمل والدك؟"
And little Billy says, "My father plays the piano
يقول بيلي: "أبي يعزف البيانو
in an opium den."
في إحدى الحانات"
So the teacher rings up the parents, and says,
فيتصل المعلم بأهله ويقول لهم
"Very shocking story from little Billy today.
لقد صعقت عندما إدعى بيلي اليوم
Just heard that he claimed that you play the piano
أن أباه يعزف البيانو
in an opium den."
في إحدى الحانات
And the father says, "I'm very sorry. Yes, it's true, I lied.
فأجاب الأب: "نعم، أنا آسف لذلك لكنني بالفعل كذبت على ولدي وأخبرته ذلك
But how can I tell an eight-year-old boy
لكن كيف تتوقع مني أن أقول لابني ذي الثماني سنوات
that his father is a politician?" (Laughter)
أنني أعمل في السياسة؟"
Now, as a politician myself, standing in front of you,
عندما أقوم بتقديم نفسي هنا أمامكم
or indeed, meeting any stranger anywhere in the world,
أو في أي مكان آخر، أمام أي شخص آخر
when I eventually reveal the nature of my profession,
وأكشف عن مهنتي كرجل سياسة
they look at me as though I'm somewhere between
يتم الحكم علي وكأنني
a snake, a monkey and an iguana,
أفعى، أو قرد ، أو إغوانا
and through all of this, I feel, strongly,
وكنتيجة لذلك أشعر
that something is going wrong.
أن هناك خطب ما
Four hundred years of maturing democracy,
لقد قمنا بتنمية الديمقراطية على مدار أربعمائة سنة
colleagues in Parliament who seem to me, as individuals,
إني أرى في زملائي في البرلمان كأفراد
reasonably impressive, an increasingly educated,
أشخاصاً مهمين، ومثقفين
energetic, informed population, and yet
مليئين بالحيوية، واعين
a deep, deep sense of disappointment.
ولكن مع ذلك يشعرون بالإحباط
My colleagues in Parliament include, in my new intake,
في منصبي الجديد، زملائي في البرلمان هم من
family doctors, businesspeople, professors,
الأطباء، رجال الأعمال، البروفيسورات
distinguished economists, historians, writers,
الاقتصاديين المميزين، المؤرخين، الكتاب
army officers ranging from colonels down to regimental sergeant majors.
ضباط الجيش من عقيد حتى رقيب أول
All of them, however, including myself, as we walk underneath
كل هؤلاء بمن فيهم أنا
those strange stone gargoyles just down the road,
نشعر أثناء قيامنا بمهامنا
feel that we've become less than the sum of our parts,
بأننا لا نؤدي المطلوب منا على أكمل وجه
feel as though we have become profoundly diminished.
لقد تولد لدينا إحساس عميق بأن أهميتنا تتلاشى
And this isn't just a problem in Britain.
وهذه المشكلة ليسست فقط في بريطانيا
It's a problem across the developing world,
إنها مشكلة البلدان المتقدمة بشكل عام
and in middle income countries too. In Jamaica,
وفي البلدان متوسطة الدخل أيضاً. في جاماياكا
for example -- look at Jamaican members of Parliament,
على سبيل المثال -- سترون أن أعضاء البرلمان فيها
you meet them, and they're often people who are
غالباً
Rhodes Scholars, who've studied at Harvard or at Princeton,
هم ممن تعلمو في جامعات كهارفرد أو برينستون
and yet, you go down to downtown Kingston,
ومع ذلك، عندما تزورون قلب مدينة كينغستون
and you are looking at one of the most depressing sites
سترون أكثر المواقع مثيرة للإحباط
that you can see in any middle-income country in the world:
في الدول ذات الدخل المتوسط في العالم
a dismal, depressing landscape
سترون مساحة مليئةً بالمباني المحترقة والمهجورة
of burnt and half-abandoned buildings.
تشعركم بالإحباط واليأس
And this has been true for 30 years, and the handover
وهو موجود منذ ثلاثين عاماً
in 1979, 1980, between one Jamaican leader who was
عندما انتقل الحكم في جامايكا عام 1979،1980 من القائد
the son of a Rhodes Scholar and a Q.C. to another
الذي كان أباه من علماء "رودس" ، إلى قائد آخر
who'd done an economics doctorate at Harvard,
حاصل على دكتوراه في الاقتصاد من هارفرد
over 800 people were killed in the streets
قتل أكثر من 800 شخص في الشوارع
in drug-related violence.
بأعمال شغب بسبب المخدرات
Ten years ago, however, the promise of democracy
منذ عشرة سنوات، بدا وكأن الوعد بالديمقراطية
seemed to be extraordinary. George W. Bush stood up
قد أخذ منحىً جدياً. حيث قال جورج بوش
in his State of the Union address in 2003
في خطابه عام 2003
and said that democracy was the force that would beat
"أن الديمقراطية كانت هي الدواء
most of the ills of the world. He said,
لمعظم الأمراض في هذا العالم". وقال أيضاً
because democratic governments respect their own people
"لأن الحكومات الديمقراطية تحترم شعبها
and respect their neighbors, freedom will bring peace.
وتحترم دول الجوار، ستحقق الحرية وسيتحقق السلام"
Distinguished academics at the same time argued that
في الوقت نفسه، كان هناك نقاش بين أكاديميين مميزين
democracies had this incredible range of side benefits.
حول الفوائد الإضافية التي يمكن جنيها من الديمقراطية
They would bring prosperity, security,
كالازدهار، والأمن،
overcome sectarian violence,
اللاعنف واللاطائفية
ensure that states would never again harbor terrorists.
والتخلص من الإرهاب
Since then, what's happened?
ما الذي حدث منذ ذلك الحين.؟
Well, what we've seen is the creation, in places like Iraq
ماحدث خلال هذه الفترة هو بناء
and Afghanistan, of democratic systems of government
أنظمة حكم ديمقراطية في العراق وأفغانستان
which haven't had any of those side benefits.
لكن هذه الأنظمة لم تحقق الفوائد الجانبية التي تحدثنا عنها
In Afghanistan, for example, we haven't just had one election
ففي أفغانستان على سبيل المثال، تم إجراء
or two elections. We've gone through three elections,
ثلاث إنتخابات
presidential and parliamentary. And what do we find?
رئاسية وبرلمانية، ومع ذلك
Do we find a flourishing civil society, a vigorous rule of law
لم نشهد ازدهاراً مدنياً ومجتمعاً متحضراً
and good security? No. What we find in Afghanistan
ولا وضعاً أمنياً جيداً، على العكس
is a judiciary that is weak and corrupt,
لقد نشأ نظام قضائي ضعيف وفاسد،
a very limited civil society which is largely ineffective,
مجتمع مدني محدود وغير كفؤ،
a media which is beginning to get onto its feet
شهدنا وسائل الإعلام لازلت تعاني للوقوف على قدميها
but a government that's deeply unpopular,
لكن الحكومة كانت بلا شعبية
perceived as being deeply corrupt, and security
ينظر إليها على أنه فاسدة، بالإضافة للوضع الأمني
that is shocking, security that's terrible.
المتردي، والسيء.
In Pakistan, in lots of sub-Saharan Africa,
في باكستان وفي الكثير من دول أفريقيا جنوب الصحراء،
again you can see democracy and elections are compatible
أيضا يمكننا رؤية ديمقراطية
with corrupt governments, with states that are unstable
يتمخض عنها أنظمة حكم فاسدة، ودول متزعزعة
and dangerous.
وخطرة.
And when I have conversations with people, I remember
وعندما أتحدث عن ذلك مع الناس، أذكر
having a conversation, for example, in Iraq,
أني، على سبيل المثال، تحدثت مع ناشط
with a community that asked me
من العراق، وقد كنا في منطقة تشهد حالة شغب
whether the riot we were seeing in front of us,
حيث كانت هناك عصابات تحاول نهب
this was a huge mob ransacking a provincial council building,
قنصلية في أحد الأقاليم، فسألني
was a sign of the new democracy.
هل هذه نتائج الديمقراطية الجديدة ؟
The same, I felt, was true in almost every single one
هذا الشعور أحسسته في كل زيارة لي
of the middle and developing countries that I went to,
إلى إحدى الدول النامية أو المتوسطة
and to some extent the same is true of us.
وإلى حد ما في دولنا المتقدمة أيضاً.
Well, what is the answer to this? Is the answer to just
حسناً، ماهو الحل لذلك.؟ هل يكون ذلك
give up on the idea of democracy?
بالتخلي عن الديمقراطية
Well, obviously not. It would be absurd
بالطبع، لا، سيكون من السخافة
if we were to engage again in the kind of operations
أن نقوم بعمليات مماثلة
we were engaged in, in Iraq and Afghanistan
للتي قمنا بها في العراق وأفغانستان
if we were to suddenly find ourselves in a situation
أو أن نجد أن أنفسنا في موقف
in which we were imposing
نفرض فيه
anything other than a democratic system.
أي شيء عدا الديمقراطية
Anything else would run contrary to our values,
أي شيء يتعارض مع قيمنا،
it would run contrary to the wishes of the people
سيتعارض مع تطلعات الشعب
on the ground, it would run contrary to our interests.
يتعارض مع اهتماماتنا
I remember in Iraq, for example, that we went through
ففي العراق على سبيل المثال أذكر أننا مررنا بفترة
a period of feeling that we should delay democracy.
اعتقدنا فيها أنه يجب تأجيل تطبيق الديمقراطية.
We went through a period of feeling that the lesson learned
اعتقدنا خلال تلك الفترة أن ما تسبب
from Bosnia was that elections held too early
بالأحداث في البوسنة، هو أن الانتخابات المبكرة
enshrined sectarian violence, enshrined extremist parties,
تسببت بالعنف الطائفي، وخلقت أحزاب متطرفة
so in Iraq in 2003 the decision was made,
لذلك اتخذنا قراراً في العراق عام 2003،
let's not have elections for two years. Let's invest in
أنه علينا تأجيل الانتخابات لسنتين. لنقوم بنشر
voter education. Let's invest in democratization.
الوعي الانتخابي، ولنستثمر في تنشئة البيئة الديمقراطية
The result was that I found stuck outside my office
وقد كانت النتيجة، أني نظرت من مكتبي لأرى
a huge crowd of people, this is actually a photograph
حشوداً من الناس، هذه الصورة
taken in Libya but I saw the same scene in Iraq
من ليبيا، لكنني أراها شبيهة لما يحصل في العراق
of people standing outside screaming for the elections,
كانت الحشود تطالب بالانتخابات
and when I went out and said, "What is wrong
وعندما تساءلت ما المشكلة
with the interim provincial council?
في مجلس الحكم المؤقت ؟
What is wrong with the people that we have chosen?
ما المشكلة في اختيارنا لهؤلاء الأشخاص؟
There is a Sunni sheikh, there's a Shiite sheikh,
لقد جمعنا بين شيوخ السنة وشيوخ الشيعة،
there's the seven -- leaders of the seven major tribes,
شيوخ العشائر السبعة الرئيسية،
there's a Christian, there's a Sabian,
المسيحيين، الصابئيين،
there are female representatives, there's every political party in this council,
ممثلين عن النساء، شملنا كل طوائف المجتمع العراقي في هذه الحكومة
what's wrong with the people that we chose?"
لكن المشكلة في اختيارنا لهؤلاء الأشخاص
The answer came, "The problem isn't the people
لم تكن أنهم الأشخاص،
that you chose. The problem is that you chose them."
بل أننا من قام باختيارهم.
I have not met, in Afghanistan, in even the most
إن جميع النشطاء في أفغانستان
remote community, anybody who does not want
من الذين التقيتهم، أرادو أن يكون لهم
a say in who governs them.
قرار في اختيار من يحكمهم
Most remote community, I have never met a villager
جميع النشطاء، لم ألتقي بقروي
who does not want a vote.
لم يرغب بالتصويت
So we need to acknowledge
علينا الاقرار
that despite the dubious statistics, despite the fact that
أنه بالرغم من الإحصاءات
84 percent of people in Britain feel politics is broken,
بالرغم من أن 84 بالمئة من البريطانيين يعتقدون أن النظام السياسي معطوب
despite the fact that when I was in Iraq, we did an opinion poll
على الرغم من أننا قمنا باستطلاع للرأي في العراق
in 2003 and asked people what political systems they preferred,
عام 2003 وسألنا الناس عن أي الأنظمة السياسية يفضلون
and the answer came back that
فكانت النتائج
seven percent wanted the United States,
أن 7 بالمئة يفضلون نظاماً مماثلاً لنظام الولايات المتحدة
five percent wanted France,
5 بالمئة لنظام فرنسا،
three percent wanted Britain,
3 بالمئة لنظام بريطانيا،
and nearly 40 percent wanted Dubai, which is, after all,
وحوالي 40 بالمئة لنظام الإمارات العربية، وهو كما نعلم
not a democratic state at all but a relatively prosperous
ليس نظاماً ديمقراطياً وإنما نظام توارث
minor monarchy, democracy is a thing of value
ملكي، علينا السعي وراء
for which we should be fighting. But in order to do so
الديمقراطية كقيمة. ولكي نحقق ذلك
we need to get away from instrumental arguments.
علينا الابتعاد عن الاختلاف حول الوسيلة.
We need to get away from saying democracy matters
علينا التخلص من فكرة أن أهمية الديمقراطية
because of the other things it brings.
فيما تحققه بعد تطبيقها
We need to get away from feeling, in the same way,
علينا التخلص أيضاً من الشعور أن،
human rights matters because of the other things it brings,
أهمية حقوق الإنسان في ما تحققه بعد احترامها،
or women's rights matters for the other things it brings.
أو أن أهمية حقوق المرأة فيما تحققه بعد ضمانها.
Why should we get away from those arguments?
أتعرفون لماذا علينا الابتعاد عن هذه الأفكار؟
Because they're very dangerous. If we set about saying,
لأنها خطيرة للغاية. لنفترض أننا على سبيل المثال،
for example, torture is wrong because it doesn't extract
أننا نقول أن التعذيب خطأ لأنه لا يؤدي
good information, or we say, you need women's rights
إلى الحصول على معلومات جيدة، أو أننا بحاجة لضمان حقوق المرأة
because it stimulates economic growth by doubling the size of the work force,
لأنها تنشط النمو الاقتصادي من خلال مضاعفة قوة العمل
you leave yourself open to the position where
في هذه الحالة، إننا نترك المجال
the government of North Korea can turn around and say,
لدولة ككوريا الشمالية لتقول:
"Well actually, we're having a lot of success extracting
"حقيقةً، بإمكاننا النجاح في الحصول
good information with our torture at the moment,"
على معلومات مفيدة عن طريق التعذيب في الوقت الحالي"
or the government of Saudi Arabia to say, "Well,
أو لحكومة السعودية أن تقول: "حسناً،
our economic growth's okay, thank you very much,
نمونا الاقتصادي جيد، شكراً جزيلاً لنصائحكم،
considerably better than yours,
لكن يبدو اقتصادنا أفضل من اقتصادكم بشكل ملحوظ،
so maybe we don't need to go ahead with this program on women's rights."
لسنا بحاجة لضمان حقوق المرأة لتحقيق ذلك".
The point about democracy is not instrumental.
الفكرة في الديمقراطية ليست مادية
It's not about the things that it brings.
ليست فيما يمكن تحقيقه عبرها.
The point about democracy is not that it delivers
الفكرة في الديمقراطية أنها تخلق
legitimate, effective, prosperous rule of law.
نظام قانون شرعي، فعّال، ومؤثر
It's not that it guarantees peace with itself or with its neighbors.
ليست الفكرة في أنها تجلب السلام للدولة داخلياً أو خارجياً
The point about democracy is intrinsic.
الفكرة في الديمقراطية هي أنها عملية
Democracy matters because it reflects an idea of equality
أهمية الديمقراطية تنبع من أنها تعكس التطبيق الفعلي للمساواة
and an idea of liberty. It reflects an idea of dignity,
والحرية. إنها تعكس ضمان كرامة المواطنين
the dignity of the individual, the idea that each individual
كرامة الأفراد، تعكس التطبيق الفعلي بأن لكل فرد
should have an equal vote, an equal say,
الحق بالتصويت، واتخاذ القرار
in the formation of their government.
في تشكيل الحكومة
But if we're really to make democracy vigorous again,
لكن إذا أردنا أن نقوي الديمقراطية من جديد،
if we're ready to revivify it, we need to get involved
إذا أردنا أن ننعش الديمقراطية، علينا الخوض
in a new project of the citizens and the politicians.
في مشروع المواطنين والساسة.
Democracy is not simply a question of structures.
الهياكل هي ليست جوهر الديمقراطية
It is a state of mind. It is an activity.
الديقراطية هي وعي فكري. هي نشاط
And part of that activity is honesty.
والصدق هو جزء من ذلك النشاط
After I speak to you today, I'm going on a radio program
بعد الحديث هنا اليوم، سأشارك في برنامج اذاعي
called "Any Questions," and the thing you will have noticed
يدعى "هل من أسئلة ؟" وما تلاحظونه
about politicians on these kinds of radio programs
على الساسة في مثل هذه البرامج
is that they never, ever say that they don't know the answer
أنه مهما كان للسؤال، فإنهم لا يقولون أنهم لا يعرفون الجواب
to a question. It doesn't matter what it is.
بغض النظر عن طبيعة السؤال.
If you ask about child tax credits, the future of the penguins
سواء كان السؤال عن اعتمادات ضرائب الاطفال، مستقبل البطاريق
in the south Antarctic, asked to hold forth on whether or not
في القطب الجنوبي، هل سيتعايشون مع الطقس أم لا
the developments in Chongqing contribute
أو كان السؤال حول التطورات في تشونغتشينغ المساهمة
to sustainable development in carbon capture,
للتنمية المستدامة في استخراج الكربون
and we will have an answer for you.
سيكون لدينا جواب للسؤال.
We need to stop that, to stop pretending to be
علينا التوقف عن اعتقادنا
omniscient beings.
أننا مخلوقات عارفة بكل شيء.
Politicians also need to learn, occasionally, to say that
على الساسة في بعض الحالات أن يتعلموا كيف يقولون
certain things that voters want, certain things that voters
أن بعض متطلبات الناخبين وبعض الأمور التي وعدنا بها
have been promised, may be things
الناخبين، قد تكون أموراً
that we cannot deliver
لا يمكن تحقيقها
or perhaps that we feel we should not deliver.
أو أننا لا نعتقد أنه يجب تحقيقها.
And the second thing we should do is understand
وما علينا فعله أيضاً هو فهم
the genius of our societies.
عبقرية مجتمعاتنا.
Our societies have never been so educated, have never
لقد شهدت مجتمعاتنا تطوراً غير مسبوق في التعليم
been so energized, have never been so healthy,
والتنظيم، والصحة
have never known so much, cared so much,
لقد شهدنا مستوىً غير مسبوق في العلم، والاهتمام
or wanted to do so much, and it is a genius of the local.
والحاجات، وهذه عبقرية يجب استثمارها.
One of the reasons why we're moving away
أحد الاسباب لابتعادنا عن
from banqueting halls such as the one in which we stand,
قاعات الاحتفالات، كهذه القاعة
banqueting halls with extraordinary images on the ceiling
ذات الصور المذهلة على السقف
of kings enthroned,
لتنصيب الملوك على عروشهم،
the entire drama played out here on this space,
القصة التي تحكيها هذه الصور في هذه القاعات
where the King of England had his head lopped off,
هي كيفية وضع التاج على رأس ملك انكلترا،
why we've moved from spaces like this, thrones like that,
السبب في انتقالنا من نظام كهذا،
towards the town hall, is we're moving more and more
إلى دور البلدية، هو أننا نقترب أكثر فأكثر
towards the energies of our people, and we need to tap that.
من طاقات شعبنا، ونريد أن نستغل تلك الطاقات.
That can mean different things in different countries.
قد يختلف معنى هذا الكلام من بلد لآخر
In Britain, it could mean looking to the French,
في بريطانيا، قد يعني ذلك الاعتبار من التجربة الفرنسية،
learning from the French,
والتعلم من الفرنسييين ،
getting directly elected mayors in place
انتخاب مباشر للمحافظين
in a French commune system.
في نظام بلديات فرنسي.
In Afghanistan, it could have meant instead of concentrating
في أفغانستان، قد يعني ذلك أنه عوضاً عن التركيز
on the big presidential and parliamentary elections,
على الانتخابات الرئاسية والبرلمانية
we should have done what was in the Afghan constitution
علينا تطبيق الدستور الأفغاني
from the very beginning, which is to get direct local elections going
من البداية، والذي ينص على إجراء انتخابات محلية
at a district level and elect people's provincial governors.
على مستوى مقاطعات لانتخاب حكومات إقليمية.
But for any of these things to work,
ولكن لنجاح أي من تلك الأفكر
the honesty in language, the local democracy,
المصداقية في اللغة ، والديمقراطية المحلية،
it's not just a question of what politicians do.
ليست حول ما يفعله الساسة
It's a question of what the citizens do.
بل حول ما يفعله المواطنون
For politicians to be honest, the public needs to allow them to be honest,
على المواطنين أن يطالبوا بمصداقية الساسة
and the media, which mediates between the politicians
على الإعلام، الذي يلعب دور الوسيط بين الشعب والساسة
and the public, needs to allow those politicians to be honest.
أن يطالب الساسة بالمصداقية.
If local democracy is to flourish, it is about the active
إذا أردنا ازدهار ديمقراطيتنا علينا السعي وراء
and informed engagement of every citizen.
المشاركة والمساهمة الفعّالة لكل مواطن
In other words, if democracy is to be rebuilt,
بعبارة أخرى، إذا أردنا إعادة هيكلة الديمقراطية
is to become again vigorous and vibrant,
إذا أردنا دعمها وجعلها نابضة بالحياة،
it is necessary not just for the public
فإنه ليس فقط من الأهمية أن يتعلم الشعب
to learn to trust their politicians,
كيف يثق بساسته،
but for the politicians to learn to trust the public.
بل أيضاً على الساسة أن يتعلمو كيف يثقون بالشعب.
Thank you very much indeed. (Applause)
شكراً لكم. ( تصفيق )